American Association for Social Security Records 5002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Association for Social Security Records
1909-1953
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Association for Social Security
5002
90.5 cubic feet
90.5 linear ft.
Bibliographies, bills (legislative records), clippings (information artifacts), scrapbooks, publications (documents).
Materials concern the movement to promote government provision of retirement, health, unemployment and other forms of social insurance and progressive social legislation.
2293613
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 28, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 19, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1927 by Abraham Epstein, the American Association for Social Security (formerly the American Association for Old Age Security) was dedicated to securing state and federal legislation to ensure adequate old age pensions, as well as unemployment and health insurance for American workers.
In 1927, Abraham Epstein organized the American Association for Old Age Security. The Association name was changed in 1933 to the American Association for Social Security and its goals and activities were widened to include unemployment insurance and health insurance.
Epstein was a reformer, editor, writer, scholar and public speaker, as well as the creative force behind the American Association for Social Security, which he directed for fifteen years as executive secretary. Old age pension legislation was the main objective of the Association.
The American Association for Social Security actively participated in the various state old age pension campaigns. For Epstein, this work with state programs was merely a means of bringing enough pressure to bear on Congress to secure federal legislation. The American Association for Social Security also sought reforms in the existing unemployment system and the enactment of a health insurance program.
Scope and Contents
Consists of Association correspondence with various individuals, societies and organizations, chiefly concerning unemployment insurance, federal social security, national health insurance, old age benefits, state laws and workmen's compensation. Also subject files which consist of published and unpublished materials having to do with health insurance, old age pensions, federal social security and unemployment relief; a card file of legislative histories of social security bills; a social legislation bibliography; copies of legislative bills; newspaper clippings which chiefly concern federal social security programs, social insurance, social security, and the Social Security Board; and miscellaneous related documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5001: American Association for Labor Legislation Records 5001 mf: American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5001 PAM: American Association for Labor Legislation Pamphlet File
Depressions -- 1929 -- United States.; Health insurance -- United States.; Unemployment insurance -- United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Old age pensions -- United States.; Social security -- United States.; Workers' compensation--United States.; Merit rating. United States.; Public welfare. Law and legislation. United States.; Social security. Law and legislation. United States.; Unemployment. United States. Effects on family.; Unemployment relief. Alabama.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. California.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Connecticut.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Illinois.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Indiana.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Kentucky.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Maryland.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Massachusetts.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Michigan.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Missouri.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Nebraska.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. New Hampshire.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. New Jersey.; Unemployment. Law and legislation. New York (State).; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. North Carolina.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Ohio.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Pennsylvania.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Rhode Island.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. South Carolina.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Tennessee.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. Wisconsin.; Unemployment relief. Oregon.; Unemployment relief. United States.; Veterans' benefits. United States.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Insurance, Health--United States.; Insurance, Unemployment--United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Old age pensions--United States.; Social security--United States.; Workers' compensation--United States.; Lobbyists.; Bakke, E. Wight. (Edward Wight), 1903-1971; Brown, J. Douglas (James Douglas), 1898-1986; Dulles, Eleanor Lansing, 1895-1996; Epstein, Abraham, 1892-1942; Falk, I. S. (Isidore Sydney), 1899-1984; Gray, Herman A.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Lebrun, Harvey; Leiserson, William; Litman, M. D.; McConnell, Francis J., Bishop; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965; Wagner, Margaret; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1877-1953; American Association for Labor Legislation; American Association for Social Security; Lincoln University (Pa.); United States. Children's Bureau.; United States. National Youth Administration.; United States. Works Progress Administration.
2293613
- Association for the Advancement of Psychotherapy, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Scope and Contents
  Routine correspondence
- Amalgamation of AASS and AALL., 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Correspondence including exchange between Associate Secretary of AASS, Solomon Bloom and Prof. Joseph Chamberlain, Edwin E. Witte re possible amalgamation
- Board and Executive Committee Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bloom, Allan (Associate Secretary of AASS), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Correspondence re Dr. Bloom's book, World of Nations
- Blanshard, Paul (NYS Insurance Dept.) Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Blake, Moe E. Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Billikopf, Jacob Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bills Paid (Misc.), 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Berger, B.W., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Correspondence re mss. on pension plans
- Benjamin, Herbert Executive Secretary of International Workers Order, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  re IWO's "Plan for Plenty" publication
- Board of Directors Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Bakke, E. Wight - Yale University Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Brandjard, I.M. (Dept. of Public Welfare, Montana), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Correspondence re proposed bill for Home Security
- Associated Industries of MASS, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Correspondence to all members re opposition to Wagner and Connery Bills
- Appeals - Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Appeals for Contributions Sample letter, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Appeals - General, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Applications for Positions Recommendations, resignations, etc., 1931-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Anniversary Celebration (10th), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondence re 10th Anniversary of the Association from many supporters including Jacob Billikopf, Hugo Black, J.P. Chamberlain, Paul Douglas, William Haber and others.
- AASS - re Work of Association (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Correspondence re NY Times article by Epstein; contributions from other organizations, unions, benefactors; response to contribution requests
- AASS - Financial Appeals and Materials on Ideas, Costs, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence with Harvey Lebrum, Acting Executive Dir. of AASS with various persons concerning fund raising; Herbert Lehman re possible publication ideas
- American Association for Social Security (AASS), Administrative Committee, 1933-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  General correspondence with John Andrews and Abraham Epstein re article in New Republic, "Enemies to Unemployment Insurance"
- American Association for Labor Legislation, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Routine correspondence with John B. Andrews, Executive Secretary
- Barradas, Gerald - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cannot Contribute Routine, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Contributions, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Contribution to Epstein Testimonial, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Lists of contributors to Abraham Epstein Testimonial Committee
- Contributions, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Contributions, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
- Contributors' Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Conferences - Outside, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Routine correspondence re conferences outside AASS
- Cohen, Wilbur (Member, Comm. on Economic Security, Staff Member of SSB, and Bureau of UC), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Christian Social Justice Fund, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  re possible grant from CSJF to AASS; appeal of decision deciding not to grant AASS funds
- Christadora House - Open Forum, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  re Health Insurance Conference held at Christadora House
- Board Members - Prospects, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Correspondence from Matthew Woll, second Vice-Pres. of AFL; C. Johnson, Pres. of the Chamber of Commerce of the U.S. re refusals of offer to become members of Board of Directors
- Chamberlain, Joseph P. (Columbia Univ.), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 36a)
  re the Unemployment Insurance Bill
- Contributions, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Byrne Condon Bill (NY), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Letters re the unemployment insurance bill
- Business - Miscellaneous, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Burton, Noble, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Incoming letter re unemployment in general
- Burns, Eveline (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Incoming letters from Eveline Burns re her observations on Epstein amendments - no date
- Burke, William W. (Washington Univ., Dept. of Social Work), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Bunker, Frank (Member, Christian Science Comm. on Publication for the District of Columbia), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  re employees who are of the Christian Science faith and social security
- Bullick, H. W., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  re article from American Seaman and social security
- Bryan, Lin (Chairman. of People's Rights Assn.), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Re gaining guidance and support from AASS
- Brown, Douglas J. (Princeton University & VP of AASS), 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Correspondence with Epstein re work of the organization; also between Brown and Bakke re coalition of social security in the country, and Altmeyer re Advisory Council of AASS
- Brown, Grace, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Correspondence re proposed bill on social security
- Chile Conference Inter-American Committee to Promote Social Security, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Division of Placement and Unemployment Insurance -Department of Labor - NYS, 1935-1943 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondence re separate reports and partial unemploy-ment compensation; correspondence from Epstein to Chief of Placement re difference between unemployment compensation and private insurance
- Constitution Amended (By-Laws, etc.), 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Copies of by-laws, constitutional amendments, constitution
- Federal Social Security - Grants - In - Aids, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Correspondence to I. S. Falk and Mrs. Eleanor L. Dulles including a study of the need to change the 50-50 matching system of Federal grants in order to be more equitable to needy, aged, blind, and dependent children
- Federal Social Security - Federalism and Federalization, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Correspondence re the pros and cons of making unemployment compensation a federal program
- Experience Rating vs. Social Security, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Paid and Complimentary Copies. Routine Correspondence
- Experience Rating vs. Social Security, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Correspondence re above article appearing in Social Security; pamphlet enclosed
- Expense Statement - Lists, Reservation Cards and Programs, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Executive Committee, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  routine correspondence
- Epstein, Henrietta, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Routine correspondence; series of letters regarding reclaiming of Mr. Epstein's files by Mrs. Epstein (after his death) with Harvey Lebrun; enclosure: "Abraham Epstein - Pioneer and Prophet" testimony to Mr. Epstein
- Federal Social Security - Pensions and Politics (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Correspondence with Margaret Wagner re candidate for Governor of Ohio Martin Davey
- Donnelly, Thomas J. (Sec. -Treas. Ohio Fed. of Labor), 1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  re Epstein's failure to attend 14th annual conf. of AASS
- Federal Social Security - Professions, Condition Of, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Routine correspondence requesting information for research work being done by Epstein on subject
- Distributist Committeemen of America, Inc., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Incoming letter asking for appointment to talk with Bishop McConnell about social security views
- Discontinued Members, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Correspondence re discontinuation of membership; contributors asking, for various reasons, that their names be removed from the list
- DeTurberville, Estee (Dept. of Social Welfare, Calif.), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Correspondence re California old age bill; possible attendance of DeTurberville at AASS Conference
- Davis, Michael W. (Board Member and Chmn. Comm. on Research in Medical Economics), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Daily Contributions, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Cumulative Trial Balances and Monthly Receipts and Expenditures, 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Corporate Matters, 1932-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 2a)
- Correspondence re Membership Lists and Prospect Lists, Membership Organizations, 1938-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Dopkin, Lee. L. - Baltimore, MD. Member of State Board of State Dept. of Public Welfare in Maryland, 1936-1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondence re Mr. Dophin's aid in securing contributions
- Folsom, Marion B., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Routine correspondence re Mr. Epstein's book and Folsom's proposals to the Advisory Council
- Health Insurance - Miscellaneous, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Correspondence from January 1938. Routine correspondence
- Health Insurance Bill, 1940, Assoc. Model (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Reactions to revised edition of the Association's Model Bill
- Health Insurance Bill (1934-35) Assoc. Model, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Reactions from a wide variety of sources to Association's draft of a model bill
- Health - Bibliography, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Routine correspondence re various articles and books dealing with health costs and insurance proposals
- Hartz, Gustov - Pamphlet, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Routine correspondence re pamphlet by German reactionary concerning social insurance
- Haas and Schlesinger - CPA's, 1930-1942 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Gray, Professor Herman A. Correspondence, 1935-1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Golden, Clinton S. Northeastern Director of Steelworkers Organizing Committee, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Correspondence re election of Golden as a VP of AASS and how this is effected by Mr. Epstein's stand on Emergency Displacement Benefits; routine matters
- Federal Social Security - Mother's Pensions, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Routine correspondence requesting information on Mother's aid legislation
- Gatewood, E., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Correspondence re national pensions and suggestions for improvement sent to Mr. Epstein
- Health Insurance Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Fitch, John A. (NY School of Social Work and Member, Executive Committee, AALL), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 31a)
  Correspondence re forming a united front in the movement for unemployment insurance
- Financial Statements - Comparison, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Financial Statements, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
- Finances - Inventory, etc., 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Fifteenth Anniversary Conference, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Routine correspondence and various enclosures dealing with post-war America and social security; authors include Arthur Altmeyer, Nelson Rockefeller, E. Wight Bakke, and William Green
- Federal Social Security Wage Records, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Correspondence from M.D. Litman to Division of Placement and Unemployment Insurance Industrial Commissioner, and Mr. Epstein complaining about injustice of the system
- Federal Social Security Taxes, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Correspondence to Altmeyer from Lebrun re the AASS stand on tax freezing, and to Senator Alben Barkley from Altmeyer re testimony to the Senate Finance Committee hearings on tax freezing; editorial by Epstein re Treasurer Secretary Morganthau's consideration of increased social security taxes
- Federal Social Security - Social Security Board, 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Notification to holders of defense contracts and routine correspondence re explanation of the Act
- Federal Social Security and Relief, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Gilbertson, H.S., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Correspondence between Gilbertson and Mr. Epstein re an alternative proposal to unemployment reserves
- Health insurance - Connecticut (Box 3, Folder 8a)
- Hoey, Jane M., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Routine correspondence re states that have passed old age assistance laws or bills
- Hillman, Sidney (Chmn. CIO PAC), 1944 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Incoming letter inviting Harvey LeBrun to CIO Conference re full employment in post WWII era
- Hicks, M., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Incoming letter re distribution of literature concerning wealth distribution programs
- Health Insurance - Rhode Island, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Correspondence re opposition to Rhode Island's proposed illness compensation bill; routine correspondence
- Health Insurance - Substitutes for Voluntary Schemes, Etc, 1929-1942 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Routine correspondence re various schemes for health insurance with some enclosures explaining those schemes
- Health Insurance - New York, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Routine correspondence; handwritten response to Gray's letter to the editor the Times calling for health insurance from a woman whose husband had been out of work for five and a half months; notes on proposed N.Y.S. Health Insurance Plan Principles
- Health Insurance, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Correspondence from Mr. Epstein to Francis Perkins, Robert Wagner, and Mayor LaGuardia re AASS's proposed health insurance program for social security; enclosure: "The Case for Health Insurance" by Mr. Epstein
- Health insurance - Medical profession - individuals, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Routine correspondence, enclosures include: "Principles and Proposals for the Improvement of Medical Care", and an address given by M. J. Tobias before the Committee on Civic policy - Medical Society of County of New York
- Insecurity - A Challenge to American Responses, 1930-1943 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Correspondence re Mr. Epstein's book - criticism, bills for payment, and buyer lists included
- Health insurance - conference, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Health insurance - conference, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Health insurance - conference, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Health insurance - Senator Arthur Capper, 1937-1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Routine correspondence re a Health Insurance Bill
- Health insurance - correspondence, 1934-1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  1934 (Jan-April) Routine correspondence
- Health insurance - correspondence, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Health insurance - correspondence, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Health Insurance - New Jersey, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and J. Douglas Brown of Princeton, and E. Wright Bakke of Yale re expansion of New Jersey's unemployment compensation system to include illness coverage
- Langer, Senator William, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Sen. Langer re bill proposed to amend the Social Security Act known as the "General Welfare Act" introduced by Langer
- Lebrun, Harvey - Personnel, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  Correspondence re hiring of personnel
- Lebrun, Harvey - Lectures, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Correspondence re lecture on U.S. Social Security given by Mr. Lebrun at the Jefferson School of Social Science
- Lebrun, Harvey - Arrangements and Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Correspondence re Mr. Lebrun's assumption of the Acting Executive Directorship of the AASS following Mr. Epstein's death; letters of recommendation, conditions of acceptance, etc.
- Leases, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- League for Industrial Democracy, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Laws (States), 1944 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  Lists of State Social Security Laws
- Latimer, Murray, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  Correspondence between Latimer and Mr. Epstein concerning questions on amendments to the Social Security law; enclosed is a copy of Latimer's bill to amend the SS Act
- Hogue, Mr. and Mrs. Richard (Dir. Independent Legislative Bureau), 1942 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Correspondence re Christian Justice Fund contribution to the AASS
- LaPorte, Alphonse A., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Incoming letter from A. LaPorte re draft, of proposed Pa. bill concerning old age assistance
- Hohaus, R.A., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Incoming letter re Mr. Hohaus's resignation as a member of AASS Advisory Committee
- Labor Unions, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Correspondence between various unions and Harvy Lebrun, Acting Executive Director, re sending of union official roster
- Kettle, Fletcher C. (Division of AA, Illinois), 1941 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Correspondence between Kettle and Mr. Epstein re study of almshouses in different states prepared by Illinois' staff, report enclosed
- Kelley, Nicholas, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Ives, Irving M. (Assemblyman), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 21a)
  re passage of Social Security Program Bill
- Internal Revenue Dept. (Mr. Hastings), 1942 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Correspondence re tax standings of AASS
- Institute, Conference, Forums, Suggestions, Etc., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Lebrun, Harvey (Prior to 1943), 1930-1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Mr. Lebrun re mutual interests in research for old age assistance and social security; Lebrun was working on his PhD. thesis during this period
- Lasker, Mrs. Alpert D., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Correspondence between Mrs. Lasker and Solomon Bloom, Associate Sec. for AASS, re financial contributions from former to latter
- Martin, H.J., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Incoming letter - scheme to aid the country's economic condition
- Minimum Wages, 1933-1939 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Reports of hours and earnings of various industries - i.e. Laundry, Clothing, in Connecticut
- Meyer, Mrs. Eugene (Editor, Washington Post), 1937-1940 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  re social security campaign; various provisions of social security program; and the publication of articles and letters in the Post
- Merit Rating in U.S. - Miscellaneous, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Merit Rating in Unemployment Insurance - Pennsylvania, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Substantive letters between Mr. Epstein and Mr. Wolf re merit systems; correspondence between Mr. Epstein and a variety of labor officials in Pennsylvania re merit rating
- Merit Rating in Unemployment Insurance - New York State, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 20)